Guide to the Peter Wood Papers on the Nixon Library Controversy, 1981, 1985
Duke University. University Archives
Peter Wood papers on the Nixon Library Controversy 1981, 1985
Duke University. University Archives
Wood, Peter H., 1943-
0.5 linear feet Extent: approx. 450 Items
Peter H. Wood is Professor Emeritus in the Dept. of History at Duke University. The collection consists of documentation related to the Nixon Library Controversy at Duke during 1981.
RL.01960
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the University Archives to use this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Peter Wood Papers on the Nixon Library Controversy were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 2012.
Historical Note
In July 1981, Terry Sanford initiated negotiations with former U. S. President Richard Nixon (Duke Law '37) to locate the Nixon presidential library on the campus of Duke University, Nixon's alma mater. When this information was revealed to faculty members during the week of August 10, 1981, many opposed the proposition, citing Sanford's failure to consult the faculty prior to initiating negotiations.
Many who opposed the library had moral objections to memorializing a President whose behavior in office was reproachable, and they feared a negative effect on the university's reputation. Other concerns included the effects of increased tourist traffic on campus and the uncertain aesthetic nature of the proposed structure. However, supporters of the Nixon Library argued that the scholarly and academic benefits of locating the Nixon Presidential Materials collection on campus should and would outweigh other concerns. These supporters tended to denounce the actions of vocal dissenters as divisive and arrogant.
Meetings of the Academic Council and Board of Trustees during September and October 1981 were dominated by the Nixon Library debate, and a group of faculty formed the Committee Against the Nixon-Duke Library (CANDL) to organize the efforts of faculty, students, alumni, and others opposed to the proposed library. Although the Academic Council voted not to pursue further negotiations with former president Nixon in a 35-34 decision at a September 3, 1981 meeting, the Board of Trustees later voted 9-2 to proceed. By April 1982, negotiations had stalled. One year later, Nixon's representatives announced that a site at Chapman College in San Clemente, California, had been chosen for the Richard M. Nixon Presidential Library.
These files were created by Peter H. Wood, while serving as Professor in the Dept. of History. He is now Professor Emeritus.
Collection Overview
This collection contains correspondence, flyers, clippings, and other documents regarding the Nixon Library Controversy at Duke during 1981. The documentation was created and/or collected by Dept. of History Professor, Peter H. Wood, and demonstrates the divisiveness of this controversy as well as the opinions of Duke faculty members regarding the Nixon library.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Duke University. Committee Against the Nixon-Duke Library; Duke University -- Faculty; Presidential Libraries -- United States; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913 -- Public opinion; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-
Related Material
Sydney Nathans Collection, 1975-1981
Duke University Archives
Committee Against the Nixon-Duke Library (CANDL) Records, 1981
Duke University Archives
Nixon Library Controversy Reference Collection, 1981-2001
Duke University Archives
Detailed Description of Collection
- Container List
  - Nixon Library: General, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Outside Duke, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Hoover Library, etc., 1981 (Box 1)
  - Teach-In, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Craufurd Goodwin Letter (from the History Dept.), 1981 (Box 1)
  - Quotes from Historians, circa 1981 (Box 1)
  - Sydney Nathans on Presidential Libraries, circa 1981 (Box 1)
  - Briefing File, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Cady Letter, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Wood's Statement to the Academic Council, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Resolution on Location: Presented to the Academic Council by Wood, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Wood's Article for the OAH Newsletter, circa 1981 (Box 1)
  - Dirk Philipsen: "Power, Politics, and a Private Elite University: The Nixon Library Controversy at Duke," circa 1985 (Box 1)
  - ITT, undated (Box 1)
  - Maps, undated (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1981 (Box 1)